[Music]
so
good evening and good day everyone
welcome to episode 12
of ask abhijit today i'm gonna answer
your questions about
world history so world history is a
fascinating
topic it is something we should all
learn more about because
studying world history helps us
understand the forces and the factors
and the various influences that shape
the course of of
events worldwide and these are the
events that eventually end us affecting
uh
and end up affecting our day-to-day
lives
so world history is a fascinating topic
i promise you it's very interesting
it's more interesting than most fiction
stories
so these are the things that we're going
to discuss today and
as always you guys have asked a lot of
wonderful
very interesting questions so i'm i have
selected a few of these questions that
you people have asked
and i'm going to take those up today and
as i get as always today is a 60 minute
session and at the end if there is time
i'm gonna take a few
uh live chat questions so let us
go right in let's dive in and let's take
the
first question so this is by akash
akash asks was the battle between sparta
and
athens true or is it part of their
mythology
good question so it is a true it is not
it's not a battle it was a war and it is
a true
true war it's a true event it's
something that happened in the 5th
century
bce so when we discuss the history it's
always
useful to take a look at the map so let
me
show you uh share the map with you
this is where we are so let me take you
to where
these events happened we are here in
india let's go
let's go westwards so this here
is the nation the modern nation of
greece
so this battle this war took place in
the
5th century bce between athens
which you see right here in the middle
of the screen and
the city of sparta which is here
so these were two coalitions between
so at the time greece was divided into
nation states
and all of these nation states were at
some time or the other
usually invariably at war with each
other they were always battling for
supremacy
so sparta was the traditional hegemonic
power in greece
it is in this peninsula which is called
the pennipolis
peninsula and this war was called the
penipulsion war
so what happened was that sparta was a
traditional power in greece
it was the hegemonic power and in the
first half of the 5th century bce
athens began to emerge as a powerful
city-state
at the time there was a conflict between
greece and persia
so much of what is east of greece
present-day anatolia etc was all
occupied by the
persian achaemenid empire the manish
dynasty
and persia was for a great deal of time
at war with the greeks
so the athenian athenians they managed
to repulse persian invasions and they
defeated the persians in several
battles and they became very powerful
and they had a greater population
so they created a confederation of
city-states and alliance of city-states
and this basically stood against the
alliance of the spartans so the spartans
had
a number of allies on the manipulation
peninsula
now athens has had a greater population
than sparta it was more powerful
it had it was able to build a much
greater army
many more uh many more infantry
soldiers than the than the uh spartans
they grew they grew a
big navy more than 300 naval ships while
sparta did not have a single ship at all
and the athenians became so powerful
that they basically uh started
extracting tribute
from their so-called alliance members
the other city-states
so they became a hegemonic dominant
power and
they posed a great deal of uh a great
threat
to the spartan alliance so the
historian thucydides who was from athens
he observed that the emergence
of athens as a new uh
as a new power threatened to displace
the existing hegemony of
sparta and he said that when such one
such a thing happens
war is inevitable and this is called the
thusey diaries trap it is something that
is relevant even today in geopolitics
whenever war is essentially inevitable
according to this principle
when an emerging power threatens to
displace
an existing great power either
on a regional level or at the
international level as
the existing hegemon so this is
currently uh
anal this is you currently used to
analyze the u.s china rival rape
so that's about uh tusi daisy it's to
see diaries
so the athenians and the spartans
basically went to war
the war happened in the second half of
the fifth century bce
it was a great drawn-out affair it
happened it it went on for almost three
decades
and there were many ups and downs many
phases of the war there were many
uh their thoughts there were many uh
ceasefires as well
there were periods of relative stability
and then they went back to war
initially athens was very powerful they
had a much greater army
they had these hoplite soldiers hoplites
were infantry men
who were very well armored and they
would have these spears
they had hot lights they had uh archers
they developed this so the
archery tactics they they uh they hired
swords uh they hired horsemen from
skithya
so they built up a great uh in
cavalry army as well and then they used
all that on their ship so they had
brilliant naval tactics
they used to put archers and hop lights
and even
cavalrymen on ships and they used this
to raid the
penipules peninsula and initially the
athenians had a great deal of success
but eventually the spartans were able to
prevail when they started adopting the
same tactics that the
athenians had so at the end of the day
at the end of the war the spartans
triumphed
because and they also had some help from
the persians from the accommodate empire
so at the end of the day at the end of
the war they were able to invade and
occupy athens and that was the end of
the war so that brought
an end to the era of athenian dominance
in greece
it brought the athenian empire
essentially crashing down for some time
in the next century there was a brief uh
resurgence of athens there was another
war
and so on the history of cycles go on so
that is in brief about the
penipulsion conflict between the greeks
and the spartans it is
very much a real conflict and it is
something that historians even today
draw uh draw lessons from
especially the thruster ideas trap which
says that when new power
emerges and threatens the hegemony of
the existing
power whoever it is then war is almost
inevitable
and that's why people believe that today
war is more or less inevitable in some
form or
the other between the americans and the
chinese
so that's in brief about this question
it's a wonderful question
okay udit asks can you tell us anything
about the life
of napoleon bonaparte that fascinates
you the most
so napoleon is a fascinating personality
this entire life is fascinating it's a
it's a very adventurous action-filled
life
and he rose out of obscurity and
achieved so much
so let me tell you just some highlights
from his life
so once again let's go to the map
because maps help a lot
so we were in greece let's go further
westwards
so this is greece now we are in italy as
you can see
and to the west of italy there is this
island called
korthika so this island was historically
owned by the
the by the genoans can you see the city
here genoa
so this city was a very wealthy city
state in ancient italy
in the middle ages etc and they owned
this
little island called corsica it's not a
little island it's a reasonably
well-sized island and it is on this
island that napoleon was born
so he was born in the town of ajasio
ajaccio or whatever it's called whatever
the pronunciation is so that's where he
was born
he was born in the year 1769
and what's interesting is that at the
time it was italian territory
and when the genovese sold the island to
france
napoleon's father fought the french for
the french he fought the french french
occupiers
so napoleon was born in napoleon
it's an italian name napoleoni
that was his real name so his father
fought the french on this island and
eventually uh the rebellion failed and
he made
his peace with the french his father
napoleon's father
and he was appointed as the emissary of
the corsican people
to the emperor of france so he went to
paris and he developed good connections
with the french
and it is these connections that enabled
napoleon the young napoleon
to go to paris and enroll to go to
france
and enroll in a military school so he
enrolled in a military military school
and
he had a lot of problems because he
spoke the corsican language he did not
speak french
he learned french quickly but he had
this thick
rural corsican accent for which he was
mercilessly teased
but it made no effect on him he was very
very strong-willed
and it was soon found that he was very
good at mathematics and logic and
tactics
especially at geometry so his tutors
advised him to join
the navy because geometry is a skill
that is very
uh very very useful in naval affairs
especially naval combat etc
so napoleon considered joining the royal
navy the british navy because he did not
feel any
particular allegiance to france but then
he decided to
join the french army the infantry the
artillery division
because even an artillery artillery you
need a great deal of geometrical
expertise in geometry projectile motion
distances and all that
so he joined the french army he was
in the artillery division and that's
when in 1789 the french revolution
happened
which was a terrible bloody affair so he
went back to korothika
for some time for a few years when the
while the revolution played itself out
in france
and then he returned
to france he rejoined the army or he
rejoined his
regiment etc and then
he had a very interesting initiation
combat so there is a city of toulon
over here in southern france on the
coast on the mediterranean coast
so this city was at the time so france
had undergone this revolution
the monarchy was overthrown a
revolutionary government was in power
and this city toulon was was held by
royalist forces and it was helped by the
british royal navy so the british royal
navy
was over here in the harbor of this
of the city they were protecting the
royalists with their
uh firepower and this was threatening to
become
a big rebellion that would uh basically
undo
the changes that the french revolution
brought about
so what napoleon did was he as a young
officer let me show the
actual uh map so as a young officer what
he did was he brought his artillery
uh regiment to this city of toulon
okay and uh and there is a hill
which overlooks the city this hill here
it's called mo fargo
so he had his his troops climbed this
hill with the artillery
he was injured in the attempt to take
the hill but he was able to take the
hill
and from here he was able to threaten
the royal navy and he was able to evict
them
from the harbor of the city and because
of that the french were able to retake
the city
and the revolution was saved and this
catapulted napoleon to a great deal of
fame
and it advanced him in his career and so
on
and then he was appointed as the uh
there was a lot of lot more developments
he even foiled an insurrection in paris
he opened fire with artillery in the
heart of paris
in the heart of paris on the
insurrectionist he
he basically killed 1400 plus people
with artillery firepower and he again
saved the revolutionary government
the revolutionary government because of
which he was given a big advancement he
was given
the charge of the army of italy so he
went into italy
he fought many battles there against the
austrians because when the revolution
happened
france lost a lot of territory outside
france which the monarchy had held
revolutions are dangerous and the these
these affairs are they cause sometimes
more harm than good to a nation
so france had lost a lot of territory in
italy he went to italy he regained all
the territory
from the austrians and that again
embellished and burnished his
credentials
after that he went to he basically went
to
egypt he wanted to cut off the british
trade routes to india
so he entered into an alliance with the
with
tipu sultan the butcher of mysore and he
invaded egypt with the with the hope of
of conquering this country and cutting
off the british trade routes to india
so he initially met great success but
eventually the british
navy under admiral nelson was able to
destroy the french fleet
and so it was an inconclusive affair so
napoleon went into
the regions of syria damascus etc and
from there he went back to france
in france he engineered a coup in paris
right he engineered a coup there and
he essentially uh became the dictator of
france
in a very short period of time he wrote
a new constitution and he proclaimed
himself consul for
life in france and he installed himself
in the
royal palace in paris and then
uh what happened was that uh many other
things happened as
i'm just going very very quickly through
history in 1802
he he uh so during the french revolution
slavery had been abolished in the french
empire
but in 1802 napoleon re-established
slavery
in the french west indies especially
haiti this place here and there was a
haitian rebellion
which actually succeeded and it drove
the french out of haiti
so napoleon found that uh and at that
time napoleon the french had a great
deal of territory
in the in the present-day united states
so napoleon found that this was too much
of a distraction so he sold
this territory to the americans to the
united states which was
at the time only limited to the east of
the country
this was called the louisiana purchase
an enormous amount of territory was sold
to the americans for about 15 million
dollars
and then uh so
so that's uh what he did in the americas
uh 19 in 1803 was the louisiana purchase
in 1804 he was proclaimed the emperor of
france he was
given the crown by the pope the pope
himself
and in 1805 he became the emperor of
italy as well
so he achieved so much in such a short
period of time
i will not go into the entire history of
napoleon it's
there's a lot more to cover but as you
can see is a fascinating
fascinating character and is one of the
most
interesting characters in in all of
world history so that's a little bit
about napoleon very interesting
character i would
recommend you study about his you read
up about his life and
history and his his career he was an
adventurer he was he had this uh
he had a guerrilla mindset he had a
mercenary mindset and
he basically came out of nowhere and
became the emperor of france
fascinating story and he was very
ambitious at the end he
tried to overreach himself and it cost
him at the end
it cost him everything but what a life
he lived what a life
so very interesting uh chapter of
history
very interesting
okay is it uh
how true are the stories regarding
gladiators in rome
did they really get freedom after
winning tournaments or were they just
slaves so gladiators were slaves they
had
no rights they were essentially property
so we we look upon rome as a great
empire a great civilization a great
powerful force in ancient history
and what we tend to disregard because of
the way we are taught history
is how oppressive
rome was it was a slave owning oligarchy
which means it was a very small number
of people
a very small group of people who held
all the power in rome
and a significant population significant
percentage
of the population of not just rome and
italy but of the entire roman empire was
slaves
so slaves were property they had no
rights
right they could be killed or used in
any manner whatsoever
and slavery began in rome with the
mythical founder of rome
romulus who decreed that fathers could
sell their children into
slavery in order to get rid of deaths
etc
so slavery was an integral part of of
roman life of roman culture
and the other interesting thing about
rome is the
gender disparity they had so the
uh gender ratio was seven in seven to
five
men to women there were seven men to
five women because of the practice
of female infanticide which was routine
and widespread
female children were not were looked
upon very poorly no one wanted a female
child
it was a burden so there was this
widespread rampant practice of female
infanticide
in rome because of which the gender
ratio was seven is to five men to women
it's incredible right and coming back to
slavery so slavery was rampant
people would be taken uh slaves by the
thousands you know when julius caesar
conquered the
goal which is present-day france he
kept i mean he he decreed people to be
slaves instantaneously the moment he
captured a town or village
50 000 people at one time immediately
became slaves and they were sold off and
julius's got richer and richer by
engaging in this
slave trade so not only did he plunder
the resources of of
the golish territories the celtic
territories of iberia of other regions
of germania
and what not not only did he plunder the
these territories for all their
resources for gold and
metals and other other valuables but he
also
set everybody to slavery and these
slaves were all
carted off to rome and they were sold
off in slave auctions
and and they were you put to different
uses
and some of them ended up as gladiators
being becoming a gladiator was also a
punishment in rome so a citizen who was
guilty of certain certain specific
crimes could be
punished to go and fight in the arena
as a gladiator so gladiators were
property they were slaves
uh very very few of them if any would
ever get their freedom
you could not just win your freedom by
winning a couple of tournaments
you were still owned by a slave owner by
a gladiator school by a stable
they were called stables like stables
for horses
so they had stables of gladiators and
the typical
life span was very short for gladiators
they had a very very intense training
regimen
and many of them would die in their
first fight in the arena
and and i think the median age at death
was
27 or thereabouts there are many
cemeteries that have been found of
gladiators
so these people usually have elongated
right arms
the bones of the right arm are usually
elongated most of them were right-handed
and they would practice they would train
with the with the sword from day to
night
because of which this deformity would
occur and left-handed gladiators were
advertised as a rarity because there
were very few
and so where does the name gladiator
come
come from it comes from the name of the
roman sword which is called the gladius
so the roman straight sword was called
the gladius
and that gave rise to the name
gladiators the ones who use the gladius
to fight
so the gladiators went through intense
training regimens they had short lives
they
ate predominantly a vegetarian diet
right
which is surprising but it has been
found to be true because they have
analyzed the
bones of gladiators from gladiator
cemeteries
and they have found through chemical
isotope analysis that the
diet was predominantly vegetarian and
with a great deal of barley and other
grains
and there was some meat but it was
mostly vegetarian
so once again these were slaves these
were property
it's a very interesting period of
history there was even a gladiator
revolution the third servile war i think
so there were three survival wars in
rome
these were slave insurrections who
slaves who tried to rise up against
the tyranny and the oppression of roman
society
so these were three separate wars in the
second and the first centuries bce
one of these was the great gladiatorial
rebellion led by a gladiator called
spartacus he was a skition from trace
trace is uh further east from rome
it's essentially uh it's essentially
western the westernmost part of turkey
and north of that
so that was not turkish at the time that
region it was a skit in the people were
mostly of skeet and extraction
are an ancient indo-iranian people so
that's a different story altogether
so a slave a gladiator named spartacus
who was a thracian origin
he led this great insurrection against
the romans this great rebellions
it actually threatened rome itself at a
point at one point
and eventually this rebellion was
crushed by the romans
and there was this great road to rome
uh i don't remember we are something we
are
i forgot the name of the road it was
lined up with crucifixes and these
gladiators were all crucified
for miles and miles as a warning to
other slaves
so rome was a brutal society a
significant percentage of the population
was slaves and only is a small
percentage of the population were
actually
given the title of citizens these were
the nobility the aristocracy
the aristocracy the land owners and the
prosperous people
everybody else was either plebeians
not libyans they were basically the
commoners non-citizens
or even worse slaves so that's in brief
about roman society very interesting
question sir
akash again akash has asked a lot of
good questions so i've taken a bunch of
those today
uh so the question is what was the prime
factor behind
the british ruling most of the world at
one time
and how did they become so strong and
greedy
so as always when an event happens in
history
there is a lot of context and causal and
there's a causal chain behind it
and that causal change can go back
centuries
so let's go back to the root of how this
all began
so in the 14th and 15th centuries
the the english where a middling small
kingdom in in europe
it was not a powerful kingdom at all the
british were a small middling kingdom
and in the beginning of the 15th century
we you had this great
not great but very famous king henry
viii
so henry viii was a king of the tudor
dynasty
he was well known for marrying many many
wives
and executing most of them eventually
and
he had this uh he had delusions of
grandeur he
he saw himself as one of the great
statesmen and conqueror of the world
conquerors of the world and he also
was had this tendency to fall in love
very often so he was initially married
to catherine of aragon who was
a spanish princess he had
a child with her a daughter named mary
and he wanted a son naturally and
catherine for whatever reason was unable
to
bear a male child for him
and so henry henry viii fell in love
with
a noble woman named anne boleyn
and he wanted to divorce catherine of
aragon and mary and bolan
now in those days i mean you would
imagine a king who could just marry
whoever he wanted but no
in europe the supreme power rested with
rome
the catholic church the vatican
and the pope was the supreme authority
in in the whole of europe
who decided what kings couldn't could
not do so
henry viii had to request the pope to
grant him
an annulment of his marriage to
catherine of aragon
and allow him to marry and bullying and
the pope
refused so that's the power the pope had
that's the power the vitacon had
they were actually the supreme power in
europe they had more power than any king
any emperor in europe
so the pope refused to grant henry
the annulment of his marriage so what
henry did was
he refuted the authority of the vatican
church he embraced protestantism
and he created a new church in england
the supreme authority of all christians
in england
the anglican church so he broke off from
the vatican
he changed his faith basically he became
he made the whole of england protestant
he started his own church the anglican
church the archbishop of
canterbury is the supreme head of this
church and
he had the marriage to catherine of
aragon arnold
and he married anne boleyn
so this broke this essentially ended the
hegemony of the catholic
church in england now it had long-term
effects
on england the catholic church had
imposed the so-called dark ages on
europe no new ideas were allowed no
science was allowed science
and anything which was not written in
the the
canonical texts of the church anything
that was not in this text was
was basically termed as satanism and it
was
punishable by death so this is the
hegemony that
ended in england and after henry
his after henry died his daughter mary
tried to revoke what henry did he she
tried to bring catholicism back
but she died in a very short period of
time and her sister
elizabeth the uh
the daughter of anne boleyn she is the
one who
restored her father's uh her father's
reforms yeah and she made england
a strong anglican country a protestant
country
and her age is called the elizabethan
age it is the age when new ideas came
into england
it's the age when new money started
coming into england from
india right so this is this is a time
when
great changes started to happen in
england so new ideas were afforded
people no longer discouraged from
thinking differently science was allowed
mathematics was allowed indian sciences
and mathematics
made their way into england in the 17th
century isaac newton would use these two
to proclaim that he has discovered
calculus and then
because of that you had the you had new
ideas and
new technologies coming into england and
all of this together
the new money the immense amount of
money that started coming in from india
the new ideas the new technologies new
sciences basically brought about the
industrial revolution
in 17th century england and you had
brilliant minds like
newton and and robert boyle and robert
hook
and the other scientists who brought
about a revolution
in the sciences and this is what
impelled
england into becoming global power the
new technology the navigation the
focus on on the navy and the sciences
that allowed the navy to
go very very much further than any other
navy had gone before
all of this made is what
made england into this global power so
it all started with
the break that uh henry viii
affected with the vatican church
now how did england become so strong and
greedy i i
explained how they became so strong how
did they become greedy well there was
they were always greedy england was
always a feudal society
a terrible caste not cast but class
system
they accuse india of casters and good
god have we seen the feudal
nature of english society there was a
time in england
around a thousand years ago when more
than 10 of the population were slaves
they had to wear this copper or brass
rings around their necks
and england has always been a land of a
great divide
you have the small aristocracy and
nobility
which was which essentially held all the
lands
and held all the power and they decided
what everything what would happen
and they decided the fate fates of the
peasants the common
the common the people the poor people so
england was
always a greedy nation they exploited
their own
people relentlessly mercilessly for
centuries they were always greedy for
expansion
and once they were empowered with the
unlimited wealth from india
and all this technology and science then
they just expanded outwards
and that's how it all happened that's
how the british
empire was born so that's a great
question
again by akash a related question the
americans are descendants of the british
and yet they fought against them for
independence please explain
so the these people have no allegiance
to anybody
the conquest of america was all for
for money it was for greed
this nation the united states was built
on the genocide of one people
the native americans at least 100
million must have died
and it was also built on the slavery of
another people the
african origin people the black people
so it was a land of immense profits
immense territories just to be stolen
away from the natives
and use the blacks to do any labor you
want give them one or two meals a day
and you're done
so it was a land of immense profits for
for this british
who went there and soon they became very
rich and very powerful
but the problem was that they owed their
allegiance to the british crown
they had to send back all the prophets
most of the much of the prophets to the
british crown
in the form of enormously heavy taxes
and they resented that very much they
said we are so many thousands of miles
away from
england why should the crown of england
have any sway
over us and that's why they fought for
independence it was the independence
they fought for the independence of a
small group of white men and their
families
the independence did not apply to the
native americans or to the
black slaves and the voting rights all
the franchise was with the white
white men only right so that's the war
for independence it is portrayed as this
great heroic struggle for justice and
equality and freedom
that's absolute nonsense uh land of the
free home of the brave that's how we
it's
america's portrayed you should see the
declaration of him of independence
in which the kind of language that is
used
for the native americans it is still
there right the declaration of
independence
so it was a very unequal brutal racist
endeavor and that was the independence
they fought for it was independence to
make
unlimited profits and pay no taxes to
the crown
of england so that is the reason they
fought
they fought to start a new empire
in the northern part in the northern
half of the
americas that's what it was and
eventually
the best minds the most adventurous
people the the political minded people
etc they all
made their way from england into the
americas so essentially
over time as the british empire declined
the american empire
uh correspondingly rose so america is in
a way
it is in a way the reincarnation or the
continuation of the british empire
it's it's the same culture the same
people and the same
mindset the same world view and the same
methodology so america is essentially a
continuation of the british empire
the empire died in the small island but
it continued in the form of the american
empire which
which was the major hegemonic power of
the 20th century
it still is to some extent but it's
declining
so that i hope answers your question
okay santoshini asks please tell us
about the war between the emperor
rimosh of mesopotamia
and the indus saraswati civilization
as was mentioned in the inscription
right so this king ramosh of mesopotamia
he was he was the
second king of the acadian empire
he he was in power in the
22nd or 20th 23rd century bce
about 4300 or so years
before today so as always let's go to
the map okay first let me show you what
this gentleman
looked like so this is believed to be a
representation
of of ramosh the second emperor of the
akkadian empire
it's a strangely familiar face
somehow isn't it okay map
so here's the map we were in in europe
let's come back eastwards
so this is present-day turkey anatolia
and this
is where rimuch reigned
let me okay this is better
so you can see kuwait here you can see
basra if you can see my mouse pointer
so this empire the acadian empire was in
power from this
this region near the persian gulf all
the way into syria and
it had it also encompassed parts of
anatolia
so it was this region over here which
you can see in my mouse
via my mouse pointer so that was the
acadian empire
and this king rimosh was the neighbor of
of another empire a proto-persian empire
which was called illum so ilam was to
the east of
of arcade of the acadians it was
essentially western uh southwest
southwestern iran so the region of the
persian gulf
over here if you can see my mouse
pointer that is that is
there was a proto-persian empire a
kingdom
and to the east of ilam you had
marahashi
which was another proto-persian region
and illam and marahashi both were
strongly influenced by
ancient india by the harappan phase of
india's civilization
so you can see if you look at the uh
artifacts archaeological artifacts
carvings statues
etc these are very very reminiscent of
what you find
in the saptas in the region during the
harappan or indus valley or saraswati
civilization era of india of indian
civilization
so ilam and marhashi were both uh
strongly influenced by
india by the by the saraswati
civilization so this guy rimosh
he was in power for about eight or nine
years only
he was the son of the great king sargon
of akkad
so rimoush fought a war with
first with the illamites and then with
the people of marahashi
so it is said that when he fought the
people the the kingdom of mar hashi
uh the marahashi uh were helped by
troops from meluha so meluha is the
ancient name that these uh
uh sumerians academic gave to the indus
valley of saraswati valley
civilization so basically indians
went and fought on behalf of the
marhashi
kingdom against uh this king
rimosh
in his inscriptions he says that he won
this war and he defeated the people of
marhashi
and their indian allies so that is what
he has
recorded that is that is the claim he
has made maybe he's right uh
that's that's what historians believe so
that is the war that he
waged against not against india but
against this uh
eastern iranian kingdom called marahashi
and the mahashi people were
helped by indian allies and even the
elamites
who had a great deal of indian influence
so that again ties in
with what we know of persia that it is a
descendant of
india the persian people are the
descendants of the parshwa
clan of the rigvedic people so we can
see
these influences right here because
indians went and helped the marasa
people who are basically
de facto persians so that's an
interesting
aspect of of ancient history uh rimosh
this king was in power for eight or nine
years only he was assassinated
and then his brother took over his
brother had a much longer and more
successful reign as the king of the
akkadian empire
so i hope that answers your question
okay soviet asks
can you please tell us the difference
between modern modern day turkey and the
turkic invaders are the
are they the same or different ethnic
groups
so essentially the question you're
asking is what is the difference between
the turks of turkey
and the turkic peoples of history so the
turkic
peoples of ancient history are the uh
are
the ancestors of the modern day turks
now if you look at the turkic peoples
who live in kazakhstan tajikistan
turkmenistan et cetera
uh and all the regions of central
asia even southern siberia etc
you will find that these people have
strongly mongol like
facial features they they they are
closest
their closest ethnic relatives are the
mongols so they have that typical
mongol style appearance right what is uh
traditionally called the
appearance
so that's what the turkic peoples of
central asia look like
if you look at the people of turkey they
look like europeans they don't look like
central asians at all
and nevertheless it is the turkic
peoples
of central asia the ancient turkic
peoples who are the ancestors of the
modern day turks
so the ancient turkic peoples where the
distant cousins of the mongols
they all both these ethnic groups
descend from the
hunnic peoples who are attested to live
in present-day eastern xinjiang
around two and a half thousand years ago
there were many hunik invasions into
india as well
and we also assimilated some of these
peoples
so the turks and the mongols are
distantly related
and the among the turks they basically
lived in central asia
now in the 13th century in the late 12th
and early 13th century when chingas khan
suddenly expanded all across the world
the turks ran for their lives and they
came they went east
they went westwards and southwards and
they entered anatolia
and that's the region they conquered and
they eventually established
the ottoman empire so there was this
king called there was a
turkic leader called suli mantra who was
the first
turk to enter anatolia so these are the
original turks
the turks of today the people of turkey
are their descendants
and these ancient turkic peoples are the
ones who invaded india as well
the various turkic invasions the mamluks
were turkic slaves
who formed the delhi sultanate and the
later the
turks who invaded the first one this new
dynasty
which was led which was initiated by
babur
he was also a turk they are now called
the mughals for
because the british called them the
mughals but they were actually turks
so the mughal dynasty is actually a
turkic dynasty so those are
also related to those people who invaded
anatolia and founded the nation
the the ottoman empire which is now the
nation of turkey
so that is the relationship between
these various turkic peoples
there are lots of different turkic
groups across central asia
turkmenistan
western present-day china which is
xinjiang which is east turkestan
and also the siberian peoples of
southern siberia etc
so these are all turkic peoples they all
speak a variety of
turkic languages which are to some
extent mutually intelligible or not
so these are the turkey people they're
spread spread across a wide
region of eurasia and the modern day
turks
are descendants of ancient turkic
peoples
i hope that clarifies this matter
good question
akash again before the first world war
which
war coast the most lives
so that's a good question that's
something we should know about so you
know
uh before the first world war there were
many many
many wars that that had a great death
toll
for example before the first world war
you had colonization colonialism
which which extracted an immense death
toll
across various parts of the world across
africa
across asia even the americas
so for example in the 1885s you from
1885 to 1908
approximately thereabouts you had the
belgian free state which was essentially
owned by
king leopold of belgium it was a congo
free state
it was in central africa and it was a
period of incredible exploitation of the
native people they were
put to work as slaves children men women
elderly everyone
children were mutilated their arms and
legs were cut off
and what not at least 10 million
africans at the very conservative
estimate
died during the belgian occupation of
the congo there was a horrible period
and then there was this scramble for
africa in the 19th century
when the whole of europe scrambled for
africa to divide up africa into small
pieces
and extract as much as they could out of
it in order to enrich
themselves so germany conducted a
genocide in namibia other countries
did all kinds of atrocities everywhere
else the french were
involved the british were involved
netherlands
uh the germans and so many other belgium
like i said
so at least at least at the very least
50 million africans would have died
in the 19th century in this colonial
occupation of africa
then you had the european colonization
of north america only in the 16th 17th
18th centuries
which cost at least 100 million lives of
the native americans
you had the british colonial colonial
occupation of india
which cost minimum 100 million lives
in relentless year after year engineered
famines
one year you would have two million
deaths one year five million another
year one million
every year you had millions of people
dying in these artificially engineered
famines
so you had at least 100 million indians
who died in that
and in the 1857 war of india
independence
at least 13 million people died in that
so that is some of the figures and then
let's look at china china has
seen enormous conflicts like i said in
another episode in the past
china is used to war but all those wars
are internal wars there are all civil
wars
china's great great military feats are
all
military feats against its own people so
you had
the typing rebellion in the 19th century
from 1850 to
1860s on thereabouts in which from
between 50 and 100 million people died
in just a decade and a half
approximately 100
million people died in china in this
typing rebellion
and then you had the transition from the
ming dynasty to the king dynasty
in the 17th century in which at least 25
million chinese died
so that's another civil war you had the
unluchan rebellion
in the 8th century in which 30 to 40
million chinese died
you had the dungan revolt again in the
19th century
in western china present in china
in which 10 to 15 million people died
mostly chinese muslims
and then outside of china you had the
conquests of timur
in which 70 to 20 million people died
and then you had the turkic invasions
and occupation of india
which is not documented at all because
india is a secular country but i would
say that at least 500 million people
died
over five centuries in india 500 million
indians
minimum during these turkic invasions
and occupation of india
so that is the kind of death toll the
world has seen it's uh
you know it kind of makes you question
humanity there is this uh
there is this theory the the violent ape
theory or something like that
which says that humans and apes are the
same we are the same aggressive uh
instincts that are inbuilt in our dna
and we could just
we just can't help it we just have to
keep fighting each other so the same
aggressive tendencies are seen among
chimpanzees
they also form groups and coalitions and
go to war against each other
their warfare is brutal and we are not
no no different
we share about 90 to 95 of the same dna
with the chimps or or at least more than
so we are very similar to our closest
evolutionary cousins and we have the
same urges
and instincts and uh aggressive
drive so all these numbers they tell you
some they kind of bring that out you
know
so that's the kind of history the
humanity has seen and i've only touched
some parts of of of recent italy history
there have been many more wars and many
more deaths and all that
so that i hope briefly and roughly
answers your question
okay this is a question by
by mr arya
how is the inca civilization of south
america related to indic
spanish archaeologists provide christian
centric data to
indigenous peruvians no serious effort
deciphering in in car language should
indian archaeologists
play a vital role sun worship is
prevalent in polytheistic faiths
though the inca civilization is medieval
so this is a question that many of you
have asked i have taken this particular
question
many of you have asked about the
relationship between india and
the ancient americas if there is any
such relationship
it's a very very interesting question
good question
so the americas the south the
southern part and the northern part two
continents have had very ancient
civilizations
uh the in-cars are a medieval
civilization they were let me show you
the map again
okay one second let me
bring the map back here it is
let me remove the question okay let's go
let's go to the americas so the inca
civilization
was in southern south western
uh in the in the north
in the northwest of south america so it
had included parts of colombia it
included it included
ecuador peru parts of bolivia parts of
chile and parts of northern argentina it
was a very large civilization
a large empire it is a pre-columbian
empire it was destroyed by the spanish
when they colonized
south america so these uh
these people they were basically like
you said polytheistic they were they
worshipped a variety of gods
the sun god is one pattern that occurs
throughout all the civilizations
of the americas the sun is always
worshipped as a god
and so is the moons or other elements of
nature
so there are male gods female gods and
it's a polytheistic culture
and other civilizations such as the
mayas the aztecs the toltecs the chimu
the moche the olmecs etc all of them
show a similar pattern they all were
polytheistic
in in nature they all worshipped a sun
god they also had other gods like the
plumed serpent
kukulkan or quetzalcoatl and many other
gods
and like you said the like somebody else
at least has said there is a great deal
of similarity between the people of
india and the people of mexico etc they
look very similar and all that
so yeah these are this is all called
circumstantial evidence there is a great
deal of circumstantial evidence
that kind of makes would wonder is there
a connection between ancient india and
these ancient peoples
of the americas and i've only spoken of
the south americas
there's a great deal of history in north
america as well
they also had great cultures and
civilizations which have
been totally ignored by historians and
archaeologists
so the question is is there a
relationship between ancient
india and these ancient peoples and the
question the answer is
there could be but as of now there is no
confirmation of that we don't have
sufficient data there was this book by
an indian author called bhikkhu chaman
lal who
brought to light lots of similarities in
culture
traditions possibly even language to
some extent
between these ancient cultures and these
peoples who still live there and ancient
india
so there is a possibility
but we don't have evidence we don't have
sufficient data to say either yes
or no can indian archaeologists play a
role
i would say that indian archaeologists
should first start playing a role in
india
they are doing nothing in india the
whole of india is unexplored from the
archaeological perspective
so we need to first explore our own
history before we can go and help others
right explore india itself gain some
experience gains and
gain some knowledge gain a great deal of
expertise in using the different
tools of archaeology especially the new
scientific tools and methods
make archaeology scientific make it a
scientific pursuit
do it extensively in india and then
maybe you can go and help
uh other cultures and countries
so in the future maybe india can do that
but first india needs to
sort out its own internal uh unsolved
historical matters so i hope that
answers your question sir
okay this is another question that i
have got uh many many times why did
hitler use the swastika symbol
so the symbol that we are referring to
as the swastika
is an ancient symbol that is found
throughout eurasia
in other episodes i have spoken about
the fact that
before the christianization of europe
the entirety of eurasia stretching from
india in the east to ireland in the west
was a single cultural continuum
you had the same culture essentially
spread across this vast region
and you had lots of different local
manifestations of this culture with
different
traditions and different names but they
were all manifestations of the same
underlying overall ancient culture and
therefore you find the swastika
everywhere in europe everywhere in every
ancient culture of europe
among the celtic people among the
gaulish people among the ostrogoths the
visigoths
uh the ancient romans the ancient greeks
uh the people of santorini island the
people of various other volcanic islands
in the mediterranean
even among the nordic people the
so-called vikings
the scandinavians the germanic peoples
everybody
used the swastika as a symbol of
divinity as a symbol of
of auspiciousness it was an auspicious
very
positive symbol and they all had
different names
from for the swastika so the
english called it the ghammadian i think
the french called it like hua game
the germans called it the hakken kreutz
and so on
so the symbol that hitler used was the
hakken kroitz
he called it the hakken kroitz the nazis
called it the hakken kroitz
it is only after the defeat of the third
reich and the death of hitler
when people rewrote history and then
they inserted the name the sanskrit name
swastika in there
so they have tried to malign the
auspicious
sacred swastika by associating it with
the symbol that hitler used
yes hitler was an aryan supremacist he
believed that the europeans were the
original aryans
right he wanted this pan-aryanist
movement
he claimed supremacy racial supremacy
for the aryan peoples
and he tried to associate this hakken
crow it's the hooked cross
with the aryan race he needed a potent
powerful symbol for his political
movement so he
took the took this hakenkroitz he
twisted it further
and turned it into a symbol of evil but
that was the hakken kroitz it was not
the indian
hindu dharmic swastika
it is later that historians inserted the
name swastika instead of the hakim croix
so that is one of the ways in which
historians have been maligning india
and hinduism so hitler did whatever he
did he was an evil man he was a monster
and they have tried to associate our
sacred auspicious symbol which is used
across
asia as a symbol of of of uh
auspiciousness they've tried to
associate the symbol with that
monster that evil monster and that is
something that we need to push back
against i mean even today you will see
that in japan
they will depict the temples vice versa
let's go to google maps again
i'll show you right away so we are in
the americas let's go to japan
this is japan let's go to an ancient
city let's say osaka
let's go into osaka and let's let's look
for temple i'm going to search for
temple
[Music]
first temple
and can you see this you have the
buddhist swastika the
reverse swastika which is used to depict
temples
across japan so that is
how auspicious this symbol is in japan
across the dharmic world across the
buddhist world
the eastern asian world and that is a
symbol these people have tried to malign
by associating it with that genocidal
monster
so this is something we need to fight
back against we need to reclaim the
swastika
as an auspicious symbol as a symbol of
good
not of evil and i think in the future i
will do a session about this ancient
symbol it's a very interesting
topic so this is a great question
okay one more question by akash if
communism and marxism failed
at every step and is responsible for
killings
of millions of people why is it popular
even today
it's because it is so easy to fool
people
especially when the fooling is done from
a position of authority
when your professors are trying to fool
you you will get fooled by them because
they represent authority and knowledge
and you believe that they they are
trying to help you out right they are
trying to educate you
and help you and that's how they pro
they propagate all this nonsense
let me explain in one sentence
what communism marxism is
marxism is a socio-political
toolkit that enables a very small number
of people
to capture and retain political power
that is what marxism is and the vast
majority of marxism practitioners
are the cannon fodder so the people who
go and demonstrate on the streets the
people who fight guerilla wars the peop
the students
in schools or in universities who go on
and do these protests etc
and vandalized property they are the
cannon fodder behind them is a small
group of masterminds
who actually understand what marxism
really is that it's a means
of capturing and retaining political
power capturing it
by any means necessary and marxism
always talks about
about about equality about the good of
the people about the equality of the
masses
about the upliftment of the oppressed
downtrodden proletariat
and the evils of the evil bourgeoisie
etc
and it is this pseudo intellectual
language that sounds like they have got
everything figured out
and that's why people are so drawn
towards marxism especially people
who feel that they have been uh they
have been oppressed in some way or they
have been
treated unfairly and that is something
that is a sentiment you can
evoke in almost anybody anywhere in the
world
you you are seeing the deep polarization
that you are seeing in the
united states it is a consequence of of
the marxist education
that uh they are getting over there so
in in brief that is why marxism is so
successful even today
because they have the power of
propaganda they have killed more than a
hundred million people
whether it is mao zedong or pol pot or
stalin or the angolan experiment with
marxism
etc it's exactly the horrifying death
toll
and yet it is it continues to be so
popular because it is used
as an instrument of acquiring political
power it's a
very powerful instrument i will go into
this in a separate session perhaps
or maybe i'll do a separate video about
this what exactly marxism is
but this is a very good question so with
that i have come to the end of the
questions i have selected let me take a
couple of
live questions if there are i can see
there are lots and lots of them
i have answered some of these questions
okay munal asks one second let me remove
that question
yes bruno asks is the earth flat or oval
uh thank you thank you brunel thank you
is the earth flat or old it's not
a complete perfect sphere it is a
distorted sphere
and if you look at the shape of the
oceans on the earth it's an
oval and this oval shape is because of
the tides
it's because of the gravitational effect
that the moon exerts on the earth
so this tidal effect causes the oceans
to bulge in two directions the sun also
exerts some gravity on the earth
and this uh this uh interplay of the
gravitational effects of the sun and the
moon
causes the shape of the oceans if you
see from far away
it it bulges out into an oval shape but
the
uh hard geography of the planet is is
more or less
spherical it's slightly extended at the
equator so it's like a squashed
sphere so it's not perfectly spherical
it's an interesting phenomenon
especially the tides are an interesting
phenomenon
so i hope that answers your question in
brief
i want to talk about history yes
in world history let me take
uh some world history questions
this is super chat
so timur was a turkic king he claimed
descent from ching's khan we have no
evidence of that
and the mughals babar
claimed to be the descendant of timur
and of chingas khan too there is a claim
when you want to aspire to greatness you
make claims
i am descended from so and so or so and
so so there is no evidence that he was
actually descended
from either timur or ching is khan and
there is no evidence that
timur was himself descended from chinese
khan even though he made the claim
so the mughals are turks babur claimed
descent from timur but that's a
hypothetical thing we don't really know
we have no evidence of that
why was samarkand the precious place to
conquer samarkand
is in a dreary hot
place it's in in the fergana valley if
i'm not mistaken
there was something especially precious
about the place it became rich because
of the conquest from india
so lots of gold and jewelry and then
precious stones and slaves from india
were taken there
to samarkand and bukhara and tashkent
and these places became rich
as a as a consequence of the
conquests of india of the various
invasions
of india so that is your answer in brief
sir
okay what would have happened this is by
milan what would have happened
if nazi germany had won the war uh how
much would the war have helped india to
gain independence
if the nazi germans if the if the
germans had won the war we would be
having this conversation
in german and
would that have helped india to gain
independence well they would have
smashed the british so india would have
gained
independence from the british but would
the germans have continued expanding
across the world and would they have
again subjected india to
occupation we don't know it's a
hypothetical scenario
uh so things would have been certainly
very different
had the nazis prevailed in the second
world war
aditya asks how did humans native people
of america
or australia reach the far distant lands
of america and canada from
and canada from africa or europe when
there were not many ways of reaching
through sea
they reached by sea they reached
these lands far away lands on canoes on
boats or rafts
or outrigger canoes i mean there was
this uh
this scandinavian explorer called thor
higher dal
who actually built an in a canoe based
on ancient designs
it was called the kontiki and he
undertook an
a voyage that either crossed the pacific
ocean or the atlantic ocean i don't
remember
right now but he crossed one of these
two oceans and he demonstrated that it
was possible to survive
such an arduous sea voyage on basically
just a raft
a primitive raft and he was able to
cross over
so it is possible to do that if you
understand navigation and if you have
some element of luck
and if you prepare properly with all the
provisions and water for this
long voyage so i think it is believed
that it is most likely that ancient
humans crossed over in that manner
i think ancient indians cross though
ancient indians during the harappan
times
had a great deal of expertise in
navigation
so it was i don't think it was very hard
for them to reach australia
but the other peoples who reached the
americas in ancient
times it would have been a much harder
challenge for them to do that
so i think they they did that on various
kinds of
primitive or quasi-primitive floating
crafts either canoes out trigger canoes
or extended drafts and that's
that's how i i think it happened it is
now known that uh
there is human there has been human
inhabitation at least
in south america for more than a hundred
thousand years more
evidence is emerging so the history of
the americas
and of the world is is changing
we are soon going to see new facts and
history may be rewritten all over again
so that's an interesting topic
this is by ritu patil thank you ritu
some people believe that the anglo-saxon
invasion much like the ait is made up
and promising there is promising
evidence to it
our anglo-saxon saxon invasion of which
place
we know that there was a saxon invasion
of the british isles
which happened about 15 or 1700 years
before today
the saxons and the angles these are two
germanic
tribal groups or ethnic groups they
invaded the british islands
they conquered much of this territory
they subdued
the local celtic peoples and they
established this
anglo-saxon rule
and culture in the british islands and
later the normans invaded
in the year 1066 under
william the conqueror duke william of
normandy
and then they imposed a french viking
composite culture on the anglo-saxons so
this is what we know it is all we have
evidence for it
if you are referring to of england okay
i get it of england so yes we have we
have substantial evidence
for the anglo-saxon invasions of
of the british islands there is
definitely a lot of evidence for
it we know it happened and the later
normal invasion also is very well
attested
so yes it is credible and there is
evidence for this
the apollo landing i don't see it i
don't think it is fake no
okay anything else
i'll take one more question and then we
will be done
okay this is about the pyramids of egypt
by webhoof
this is the last question for today
people so why are these
why pyramids like egypt were not made in
ancient india
well there is a very good reason for it
making
building a pyramid of that size is an
extremely
expensive endeavor and a great deal of
labor manpower
money gold treasure and time has to be
expended
on building a pyramidal monument which
serves no purpose to the people or the
nation
it simply serves to glorify
the emperor now india's emperors
were not like that they had to follow
a code of conduct a code of ethics
they basically served dharma and they
served the people
and the kingdom or the nation or the
civilization depending on whether it was
a small king
a big king or an emperor of the whole of
india
so they served the people they served
the nation the civilization
and they served dharma and according to
dharma you cannot have this sort of
wasteful expenditure
you have to prioritize the long-term
prosperity and security of the people
and the kingdom
and building a pyramid like the egyptian
pyramids does not serve
that cause in any way whatsoever it
actually detracts from that cause
you're wasting a lot of money and time
and all that in building a monument
to glorify yourself indian kings never
glorified themselves that's why we don't
have any
great palaces in india kings even
emperors lived
humbly and you will see that all the
time even recent kings and emperors
a great king like shivaji the great
satapathy shivaji
did he have a palace he had fortresses
because he had to fight back the mughals
the turks
so fortresses were not palaces those
were military strongholds
but he himself did not live in a
palacian palacial uh
palace or anything he lived humbly queen
herya by hulkar
she lived very humbly every indian king
or queen
lived humbly they did not have opulent
uh
show of uh palaces and all that
even in the harappan or uh region uh
phase of india civilization the biggest
buildings you will find are public
buildings
meeting places or or public baths
and all that there is no evidence of a
single palace
in the entirety of the geography of the
sabtas in the region
in the saraswati and indus valleys and
the other valleys of the region
so indian kings and queens and emperors
have
never ever wasted money in this manner
their only focus their only
duty has been to further the
national interest and to serve the
people and the civilization
and their highest morality was the
long-term priests
peace and prosperity of the people and
the kingdom
so that's the reason why pyramids like
egypt were never made
in ancient india all right
people we have come to the end of
today's session
great session great questions and this
is the first of many sessions that we
will do
about world history so that's it for
today and i
look forward to seeing you in tomorrow's
episode
thank you very much for watching have a
good night have a good day
and i'll see you i'll see you tomorrow
bye